<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the worshipful mayor of Bridgewater, and several other members of that ancient corporation, in the county of Somerset At a lecture design'd for reformation of manners. By John Cumming M.A. minister of the gospel in Shepton-Mallet, in the same county.</title>
            <author>Cumming, John, minister of the gospel in Shepton-Mallet.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81177</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230231</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899561</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899561</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81177)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2387:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the worshipful mayor of Bridgewater, and several other members of that ancient corporation, in the county of Somerset At a lecture design'd for reformation of manners. By John Cumming M.A. minister of the gospel in Shepton-Mallet, in the same county.</title>
                  <author>Cumming, John, minister of the gospel in Shepton-Mallet.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Browne, bookseller in Shepton-Mallet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1641-1700 reel 2387 cropped with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Congregational Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation II, 2 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Manners and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153890:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Worſhipful MAYOR of <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> And ſeveral other Members of that Ancient CORPORATION, in the County of <hi>SOMERSET.</hi> At a <hi>Lecture</hi> Deſign'd for Reformation of <hi>Manners.</hi> By <hi>Iohn Cumming</hi> M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Shepton-Mallet,</hi> in the ſame County.</p>
            <q>Becauſe thine Heart was tender, and thou didst humble thy ſelf before God; I have even heard thee alſo, ſaith the Lord. <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Chron. 34.27.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Shouldſt thou help the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, and love them that hate the Lord? Therefore is Wrath upon thee, from before the Lord, <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Chron. 19.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Proponamus oportet finem ſummi boni, ad queminita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, ad quem omne factum noſtrum dictumque re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiciat, veluti navigantibus ad aliquod Sidus dirigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus eſt curſus. <bibl>Vita ſine propoſito vaga eſt, <hi>Sen.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Tho. Browne,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Shepton-Mallet,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153890:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153890:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful, GEORGE BALCH, Eſq; MAYOR of <hi>Bridgewater.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> know, that a Life full of Vertue, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and equal in the Profeſſion and Holy exerciſes of Religion, is what our bleſſed Lord hath recommended to his Diſciples, as the way to eternal Happineſs; and how unbecoming a Chriſtian it is to give looſe reins to his own Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, or take pleaſure in thoſe that do ſo.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that no occaſion hath preſented, ſince You were called to a Publick and Honourable Station, to do GOD and your Country Service, but you have embraced with Zeal, and managed with Prudence.</p>
            <p>As God hath preſerved his Covenant in your Houſe, and recommended the Religion you Profeſs, by the Pious Example of ſo worthy a Father, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Vanity of the World, nor the influence of a degenerate Age, hath had any power on You, to do any thing unworthy of your Self, of your Family, or of Religion.</p>
            <p>This watchful Conduct no doubt, hath fixed the eyes of the People on You, and captivated their Hearts.</p>
            <p>Go on Sir, in your Zeal for GOD, in your ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous tenderneſs of the good of Mankind; in your watchfulneſs over your Self, in your ſpecial Reſpect to ſuch as Fear God, and in your Holy diſdain, and contempt of Sinners; And let this be your <hi>Motto, <hi>Valiant for the Truth.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153890:3"/>
            <p>Nothing but your Zeal for God, and Ardent wiſhes for the Reformation of our degenerate Age, could move You to Requeſt the Publiſhing of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe, (and I doubt not but it was Your leading the way that provoked others to joyn with You in the ſame Requeſt) which Requeſt I have now yielded to, after ſome ſtruglings with my ſelf to commit to the Publick, what I fear hath not much more to Recommend it, but Your candid Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the charity of the Auditors, before whom it was delivered.</p>
            <p>However Sir, the Friendſhip wherewith You are pleaſed to Honour me, with a faint hope, that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence may deſign Benefit to ſome by it, hath ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured its fortune in the world.</p>
            <p>If it may in the leaſt Anſwer the deſign for which it was intended, the awakening any to a Zeal for God, his Truth, &amp; that Reformed Religion we Profeſs, I ſhall bleſs God that ever it was Preached or Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, how little ſoever it doth pleaſe the Curious, or what Cenſures ſoever I incur on its account.</p>
            <p>I leave it therefore, Sir, ſuch as it is, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, and under Your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrage. And that God may Honour, and ſet You more and more to do him Service, and multiply his Bleſſings of all ſorts upon Your Family, is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR</salute>
               <signed>Your much Obliged and Faithful Servant, <hi>John Cumming.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Shepton-Mallet,</hi> 
                  <date>June <hi>19. 99.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:153890:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. II. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And how thou canſt not bear them which are evil.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is an undeniable Demonſtration of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Perfection of the Divine Being, and among other things, of his Eſſential Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, That on the one hand, <hi>he loveth the righteous, and looketh with Complacency upon the upright,</hi> Pſa. 11.7.146.8. and on the other hand, he is of purer Eyes, than to behold Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; nay, he <hi>hateth all the workers of Iniquity, Hab.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 5.5.</p>
            <p>God ſtandeth in need of nothing out of himſelf, (being Perfection it ſelf) to make him happy, or to add to his Joy and Pleaſure; yet he is pleaſed to delight himſelf with the derided and imperfect Holineſs of his Creatures. He is pleaſed with the rude Draughts of his own Image, and taketh Complacency to magnifie himſelf, his Juſtice, Holineſs and Mercy, in the way of Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>But he cannot deny himſelf, whatever Sinners do; nor is he a God, whatever ſinners think, that hath pleaſure in wickedneſs. No, he is Holy and Juſt; Evil dwelleth not with him, neither ſhall the fooliſh ſtand in his ſight. His eſſential Righteouſneſs is ſuch, that as he loveth Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and the Righteous, ſo he hateth Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the wicked as ſuch.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153890:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>All this is undeniable from the due Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the divine Perfections, from the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God's Will contained in the Scriptures, from his Approbation and Commendation of the Righteous, and his Diſpleaſure, and declared Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of the ungodly; and finally, from the great rewards laid up in ſtore for the one, and the heavy Judgements threatned to, and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly inflicted on the other.</p>
            <p>From all we may ſee, how tender God is of, and zealous for his own glory. And that it is in his will and pleaſure, That rational Beings, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſuch as eſpouſe Religion and Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhould herein reſemble and imitate him, you may learn, (amidſt other things) from the words of the Text; the Commendation of the Angel of the Church at <hi>Epheſus, I know thy Works, and thy Labour, and thy Patience; and how thou canſt not bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many things commended in this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel and Church; but that which I ſhall confine my ſelf to at preſent, is, that part of the lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Character, which reſpects a Zeal againſt Sinners as ſuch, <hi>And how thou canſt not bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to which Words, I ſhall meddle no further with the Context, than I judge abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary, to ſhew the Connection and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence. Let me only put you in mind, that valuable Interpreters look upon theſe ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> (to which you find Epiſtles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in this and the following Chapter) as typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal of the ſtate of the Church, from the Infancy
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153890:4"/>of Chriſtianity to the end of the World. And if ſo, then each Church, or the Church in its ſeveral Periods, may learn from theſe Epiſtles, what is of the greateſt Concern, with reſpect to Faith and Manners; more eſpecially, what with relation to Mens Actions is praiſe-worthy and rewardable, and what reproveable and liable to a Divine Cenſure.</p>
            <p>This being premiſed, let us haſten to the words which are a part of the Commendation of the Angel, and Church of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> I ſhall not enter upon the diſpute, whether the Term <hi>Angel</hi> is to be taken for any particular, ſuperiour Miniſter, in this and the other Churches; or collectively, for all the Miniſters in them. It ſhall ſuffice at preſent, to acquaint you, that the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifieth no more than a Meſſenger; and this is common to all Miniſters to be God's Meſſengers.</p>
            <p>Now the Character of this Meſſenger or Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, and probably of that Church, whoſe Angel or Angels he or they were, is as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>I know thy Works, and thy Labour, and thy Patience, And how thou canſt not bear them which are evil,</hi> and ſo forth. Tho' it is one Branch of this Character, I deſign to inſiſt upon; yet, becauſe of the coherence, I muſt briefly conſider the Verſe from the Beginning, <hi>I know thy works,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here you have, 1ſt. The Perſon ſpeaking: <hi>I,</hi> He that holdeth the ſeven Stars in his right hand, who walketh in the midſt of the ſeven golden Candleſticks; as in the preceding Verſe. This was Jeſus Chriſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153890:5"/>find by conſulting the firſt Chapter throughout. The Perſon is expreſſed in your Tranſlation, but in the original couched or implyed in the verb <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 2dly. What is affirmed of him, <hi>I know thy Works, and thy Labour,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I know.</hi> Now this Knowledge may have different Acceptations, as it reſpects Works in general, or ſuch as are good or bad in particular.</p>
            <p n="1">I. As it reſpects Works in <hi>general,</hi> it ſignifieth Chriſt's Omniſciency: And ſo the meaning of the Phraſe, <hi>I know thy Works,</hi> (which we have in the Front of every one of the ſeven Epiſtles) I ſay, the meaning will be, That Jeſus Chriſt had a full Knowledge or Comprehenſion of all the Works of this Angel or Church, whether good or evil; and ſo of all the others: Nothing was hid from him. And this was a manifeſt Proof, 1ſt. Of his Divinity, and conſequently that his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was omniſcience, and his Teſtimony be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all exception. 2dly. That the greateſt Fear and Reverence were due to him, as the Searcher of Hearts, and Witneſs of all Actions: But then,</p>
            <p n="2">II. As the Knowledge of Chriſt reſpects <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular good Works,</hi> it ſignifies not only Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and a full Comprehenſion, but an Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Commendation; and ſo the Word is to be taken in this Verſe. Chriſt not only knew, but he approved and commended at large the Works of the Angel and Church of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> Therefore it follows, that they were good and praiſe-worthy; for the Holy and Juſt one, tho' <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> things, approveth or commendeth
<pb facs="tcp:153890:5"/>nothing but what is approveable and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p n="3">III. As the Knowledge of Chriſt reſpects par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular evil works, it ſignifieth Omniſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Averſation: As he knows, delights in, approves and encourages good works; ſo he knows, hates and witneſſeth againſt thoſe works that are evil. As all things are naked before him, ſo of all Men in general, and of the good and bad in particular; he can ſay, <hi>I know thy Works.</hi> And as the Works are good or bad, ſo he approveth or diſliketh them, ſo he commends or reproves; I may ſay, ſo he rewardeth or puniſheth the Workers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What is approved and commended in this Angel and Church; and indeed, approveable and commendable in any other, either Church, Angel or Chriſtian, according to his reſpective capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Good works in general, and labour, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and a zeal and warmth for God, and againſt Sinners as ſuch, in particular. <hi>I know thy Works, and thy Labour, and thy Patience; and how thou canſt not bear them which are evil.</hi> That by Works here, we are to underſtand good Works, appears by the following particular induction; <hi>thy Labour, thy Patience; and how thou canſt not bear them which are evil,</hi> and ſo forth. One commendable branch whereof was, 1. <hi>Labour,</hi> that is, an active endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and diligence to propagate the Goſpel. 2. Another was <hi>Patience</hi> in ſuffering, or in bearing the Croſs for the Goſpel. Some think, There is here a Hendiadys; and that thy <hi>Labour,</hi> and <hi>thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> ſignifieth only thy Patience in Labour:
<pb facs="tcp:153890:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But this makes no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, both Senſes level at the ſame Scope. The 3d. part of the commendable Character, &amp; what we are now to ſpeak to, followeth: <hi>And how thou canſt not bear them which are evil. I know,</hi> that is, I approve, <hi>how thou canſt not bear them which are evil.</hi> So the Context will warrant us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. <hi>I know how thou canſt not</hi> — Now it may be ſaid of one that he cannot do, not only that which exceedeth his natural Power, but what he cannot do without Reluctancy, Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, or with any Delight or Pleaſure. So here, Thou canſt bear, that is, Thou canſt not patiently bear: Or, it is a great grief and trouble to thee to bear: It is againſt thy Mind and Heart, or ſuch a thing as thou canſt with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience endure. Them which are evil, that is, ſcandalous Sinners; Perſons erroneous in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or lewd and wicked in Life and Coverſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So the ſtream of Interpreters run, <hi>Grot. Cluv. Med. Par.</hi> Now, what is approved &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended; and is indeed, approveable &amp; commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all Chriſtian Churches, Kingdoms, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths, and particular Chriſtians in their ſeveral Spheres, is a Zeal and Warmth for God and Religion, and againſt Sin and Sinners as ſuch. <hi>I know, how thou canſt not bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the words thus conſidered and opened, I ſhall lay down this poſition, as a foundation to build upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> It is not only a laudable Character, but the indiſpenſable Duty of all Chriſtians, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſuch as are intruſted with Government in a
<pb facs="tcp:153890:6"/>Chriſtian Church, Kingdom or Commonwealth, to diſcover a Zeal for God, and a Holy Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt Sinners as ſuch. <hi>I know, how thou canſt not bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To illuſtrate and confirm this Poſition, (ſo ſelf evident and agreeable to Scripture in all its parts, and the Character and Practice of the greateſt Saints and Reformers) I ſhall take the following particulars under conſideration; or ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is implyed in that Zeal for God, and Holy Indignation againſt Sinners as ſuch, ſet forth in the Text by not being able to <hi>bear them which are evil.</hi> 2. That ſuch a Zeal is not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, but the Duty of all Chriſtians; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of Chriſtian Rulers, whether Civil or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical. 3. What means are to be uſed in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Conſciencious performance of this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; or the diſcovery of a Zeal for God, and a Holy Indignation againſt Sinners as ſuch.</p>
            <p>Theſe particulars contain the Subſtance of the Doctrine; and will, if duly handled, give you the Scope and drift of the Text. I ſhall therefore haſten to their Conſideration, and that in order to a practical Application of the whole: <hi>Thou canſt not bear</hi>—</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then conſider we what is implyed in that Zeal for God, and Holy Indignation againſt Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as ſuch, ſet forth here by not being able to <hi>bear them which are evil;</hi> or ſuch as are erroneous in Judgment, or prophane and wicked in their Lives. <hi>Thou canſt not,</hi> &amp;c. This implys, 1. A great concern for the Glory of God, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his Kingdom in the World: Or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153890:7"/>which is the ſame, a valiant appearance for the Truth, and the Honour and Glory of God. The Glory of God is ſullied and underminded, and his Kingdom overthrown by the prophaneneſs and licentiouſneſs of Sinners, as far as in them lies. Such Sinners in their works deny his Being, and reject his Government. <hi>In their Works they deny him.</hi> Tit. 1.16. <hi>They ſay in their Hearts, There is no God.</hi> Pſal. 14.1. They deny him Honour and Obedience, tho' he is their rightful Lord. They will not have him to Reign over them; nay, they War againſt Him. Now, who hath any concern for Gods Glory, or Kingdom, but muſt diſcover his Zeal, and a Holy Indignation againſt ſuch Sinners? What ſhould be ſo dear to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, as the Glory of God, &amp; the honour and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his Kingdom? <hi>Do not I hate them, O Lord, that hate thee? And am not I grieved with them that riſe up againſt thee?</hi> Pſ. 139.21. The Glory of God is the end of our being. It deſerves the ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſtrength of our Affections: We are taught to give it the preference in our Devotions: And we are to ſeek it in the firſt place in all our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It naturally follows then, That we ſhould be greatly concerned for it; and conſequently filled with the greateſt Indignation againſt the inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thereof. God's Enemies as ſuch ought to be ours alſo: And nothing more diſcovers our Love to God, than that we cannot <hi>bear them which are evil;</hi> that is, them that are ungodly and enemies to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A real hatred and abhorrence of Sin. The Wicked, Ungodly and Prophane are hateful, not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153890:7"/>as Men, but as Sinners and Rebels againſt their Maker. And what maketh them hateful unto God, ſhould make them unſufferable to all that bear his Image. He that really hateth the Sin, will never indulge and cheriſh the Sinner. <hi>I will not know a wicked Perſon,</hi> ſaith the Holy David, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.4. <hi>He that worketh deceit, ſhall not dwell in my Houſe. I will early deſtroy all the Wicked of the Land, that I may cut off all wicked doers from the City of the Lord, ver.</hi> 7. and 8. <hi>ibid.</hi> Thus a gracious Soul in his reſpective capacity, whether a private Perſon, Magiſtrate or Miniſter, cannot <hi>bear them which are evil.</hi> According to his abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Sin, his Indignation manifeſts it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sinner; either by a ſeaſonable reproof, a withdrawing from his Society, a refuſal to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with him, ſome teſtimony of diſlike, or bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Offender to Juſtice, by ſhame or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thus a Holy Indignation againſt Sinners as ſuch, diſcovers the curſed nature of Sin, and how hateful it is to a gracious Soul. And <hi>e contra,</hi> a connivance at the Sinner, argues ſome reſpect unto the Sin. It was <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi>'s foul blot and blackeſt ſpot, that he loved them that hated the Lord. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 19.2. <hi>ſhouldeſt thou help the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and love them that hate the Lord? Therfeore is wrath upon thee from before the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. All lawful endeavours to reform, or in caſe of obſtinacy to reſtrain Sinners in their courſes: Who would not deſire and endeavour the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Sinners, if poſſible? Under the old and ſevereſt diſpenſation, the very Cities to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, had firſt peace proclaimed to them. If
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153890:8"/>there is the leaſt hope of Reformation, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, Reproof or otherwiſe; how happily are ſuch endeavours uſed? He that turneth a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from the evil of his way, ſaveth a Soul from Hell. And to this end we ſhould neither ſpare our prayers, nor our moſt earneſt endeavours, every one in his place and Station. But if this will not do, as we regard God's Honour, our own Duty, the good of Sinners, or the happineſs of Mankind, we muſt labour to reſtrain and ſuppreſs growing wickedneſs, every one according to his place and ſtation: For no plague ſo ſpreading and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as Sin: No evil ſo threatning to the private and publick; to Families, Churches and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. It is a curſed and bitter root, the reproach of any People, an Evil attended with dreadful conſequences and effects. It therefore highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns every one to endeavour to reſtrain the courſe and ſpreading thereof. This ſhould be the great care and work of Maſters in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, of Miniſters in the Churches, of Magiſtrates in the Commonwealth, and of all Perſons in their ſeveral places. And how much good might be done, if all did joyn hand in hand in this Work? Then ſhould we glory not in the empty Name of the Reformed, but in a happy Reformation. The plague would ſtop, and Sinners would appear as Theeves and Robbers, were they on all hands purſued with the hue and cry. When all in their ſeveral places ſet up their ſtandard againſt Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and prophaneneſs, when Miniſters uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right the Keys of Doctrine and Diſcipline, and live down Sin; when Chriſtians teſtify againſt,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153890:8"/>and arraign it on all occaſions; and Magiſtrates are a terrour to evil works; and as Miniſters of God and Divinely appointed Revengers exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Wrath upon incorrigible Sinners and evil Doers: Then there may be ſome hope of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; then may it be ſaid of all, That they are Zealous for God, Valiant for the Truth, and Active to reſtrain and ſtop the torrent of growing Wickedneſs: Or as it is in the Text, that they <hi>cannot bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who but ſuch as delight in devaſtations can ſtand unconcerned to ſee a devouring Fire, ſpread and conſume all before it? In ſuch a caſe, what hands are at work? What endeavours uſed? All bring their Buckets and offer their Service. And is not the danger as great, or greater, when Sin breaks in upon a Land as a Flood? When it runs as Lightning, and kills like the Plague? When it ſpreads as a Gangrene, and eats like a Cancer? In a word, when Iniquity abounds, and the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Sinners is daily increaſed, Who ſhould not then ſtand in the Gap, and appear for God? Who ſhould not endeavour to bind up the hands of Self-murtherers, and to reſtrain the courſe of ſuch Sinners, as are not only thorns and briers in the ſides of the Church, but a plague unto the World? Surely when Sinners turn obſtinate and reſolute againſt Reformation, 'tis high time for ſuch as fear God to appear for him, and manifeſt a Zeal for his Glory. And ſhould they not, conſidering how good their Cauſe is, be as active for God, as others are or can be for the Devil? Methinks all Chriſtians ſhould be ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153890:9"/>of the Character of the Text, <hi>Thou canſt not bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus a true zeal for God, diſcovers not only a Concern for his Glory, and a Hatred of Sin, but ſtirs up to all lawful and poſſible Endeavours to reform or reſtrain Sinners in their wicked Courſes. So much at leaſt is emplyed in not being able to <hi>bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Conſider we, That ſuch a zeal is not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, but the Duty of all Chriſtians; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of Chriſtian Rulers, whether Civil or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical. All Chriſtians in general, in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places, are bound by their allegiance, to declare their Love and Loyalty to God, and their hatred of his Enemies, <hi>It is good to be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly affected always in a good thing, Gal.</hi> 4.18. And what better thing than the purſuing of Gods Glory in the reformation of Sinners: Moreover, this zeal for God, is one of the Effects and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of true Repentance, or <hi>a godly Sorrow,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. Yea, what zeal? It is a Frame moſt contrary to a lukewarm and <hi>Laodicean</hi> Spirit, than which nothing is more hateful unto God: And therefore, Sinners of ſuch a temper, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to this, inſtead of all other Duties; and that, becauſe indeed a pious and regular Zeal leads to all other holy Performances. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19, <hi>Be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was that which made <hi>Phinehas</hi> famous to all Generations, and gained him the Covenant of an everlaſting Prieſt-hood: He was zealous for his God, and againſt theſe bold Sinners <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Coſbi, Numb.</hi> 25. <hi>verſe</hi> 8, 15. This ſeems
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153890:9"/>to have been <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Boaſt, or matter of glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he pleads it twice before God in a Breath; <hi>I have been very jealous,</hi> (ſurely it was his Zeal that made him ſo) <hi>for the Lord God of Hoſts; for the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>have forſaken thy Covenant,</hi> 1 Kings 19. ver. 10, 14. This was that which gained the higheſt Character from the Spirit of God to <hi>David, Aſa, Jehoſaphat, Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi> above all other Kings; they zealouſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced a Reformation. This is the great Glory of the promoters of Reformation in any and all Ages; and an Argument of the greateſt ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and faithfulneſs in Gods Service. It is what the Religious <hi>Nehemiah</hi> (and the ſame may be ſaid of other Reformers) took much comfort in, in his Reflections upon, and Examination of his former Life. <hi>Remember me, O God,</hi> (ſaith he) when he had been reforming and cleanſing the People, and manifeſting his zeal againſt the prophanation of the Sabbath. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.31. What ſhall I ſay? It was one of the great and crying ſins of <hi>Judah;</hi> and what forced ſuch floods of tears from the fervent Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> That the people <hi>bent their tongues for lies, but were not valiant for the truth upon the Earth,</hi> Jer. 9.3. Surely then to be zealous for God, is a duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon all, high and low, that eſpouſe the intereſt of God and Religion.</p>
            <p>But that Chriſtian Rulers, whether Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, ſhould more eſpecially diſcover a zeal for God, and the reformation of Sinners; that they ſhould in their reſpective places, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to caſt off all evil doers from the City
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153890:10"/>of the Lord; will further appear by conſidering, that,</p>
            <p n="1">I. Their function and places call them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in a more eminent manner for God. Such are God's mouth unto, and his repreſentatives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people: God hath raiſed them unto ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour above others, and inveſted them with Power and Authority, in order to inſtruct, rule, reform and puniſh Sinners. It is their work, &amp; the very deſign of their office, to ſtop the current of Prophaneneſs, to promote Righteouſneſs, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance Sin, and maintain the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</p>
            <p>Therefore they are to lay themſelves out for God. The Miniſter to reprove, rebuke, exhort with all Authority: And the Magiſtrate to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain juſtice and good order, and to diſtribute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and puniſhments: For he is the Miniſter of God, a Revenger to execute Wrath upon him that doth evil. Hence it is, he is ſaid <hi>not to bear the Sword in vain,</hi> Rom. 13.4. Let ſuch Rulers conſider the great end of Providence, in calling them to Authority over and above others; and they need no more to diſcover or prompt them to their duty to be zealous for that God, by whom they rule, and to whom they muſt be accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for the faithful diſcharge of their places: For to bear patiently them which are evil, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage or connive at Sinners; what is it, but to contradict the end and great deſign of their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice?</p>
            <p n="2">II. By not oppoſing and appearing zealouſly againſt ſpreading wickedneſs, they involve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:153890:10"/>in the guilt of the abominations and ſins committed in the places where they Live and bear Rule. <hi>Malum qui non prohibet cum poteſt, Jubet;</hi> ſaith the Moraliſt; he that ſuffereth Sin to be committed, when it is in his power to hinder it, is equally guilty with the acter: And the guilt is ſo much the greater as any is in authority or power to do God Service. A Miniſters People, is in a manner his Family; and a People within a Magiſtrates Juridiction, is his alſo. If it is in their power therefore to command good order, and reform the one or the other, and they do it not; what is this but to encourage ſinners in their wickedneſs? Is it not to become publick Patrons of Sin, and conſequently to contract publick Guilt? <hi>Elie</hi>'s great Sin was, that when his Sons made themſelves vile, he reſtrained them not. Therefore ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will Judge his Houſe for ever,</hi> 1. Sam. 3.13 how far this concerneth all in Authority, who alſo are Fathers in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places, let them conſider. I am ſure, he payed dear for his negligence, and it is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for admonition to others.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Much may be done to reſtrain growing Impiety, and prevent impending Judgments, when Men in authority perform the duty of their places. Sinners are greatly diſcouraged when they ſee others brought to ſhame or puniſhment, and that there is no tranſgreſſing with Impunity. The zeal of two ſuch Witneſſes, as a Religious Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, doth not only torment, but terrify the boldeſt Sons of <hi>Belial.</hi> And for encouragement, Acts of Juſtice are a Sacrifice
<pb facs="tcp:153890:11"/>acceptable unto God, and ſometimes as an atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the moſt crying Sins; as in the caſe of <hi>Phinehas.</hi> But ſuppoſing a People incorrigible and equally regardleſs of the Authority of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Magiſtrates and Miniſters, (which is the ſaddeſt caſe, &amp; the worſt that can be ſuppoſed) yet what comfort will it prove unto ſuch Rulers that they have done their duty? It is not of them that Sin groweth, or Sinners multiply? They ſtood in the Gap, and their great Affliction was, that the Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> were too hard for them. But however, as faithful Witneſſes, and in ſome ſenſe Martyrs, they ſhall have their Souls for a prey. God is not unfaithful to forget their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and zeal for his Glory.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. A hatred of Sinners, &amp; a reſtraint of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs makes Rulers a publick bleſſing unto any People. By righteouſneſs a Nation is exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Sin is not only a reproach, but a ſore and threatning evil. Then it is, <hi>The wicked walk on every ſide, when vile Men are exalted</hi> Pſal. 12.8. Then ſinners multiply, and ſin appears bare faced: And the conſequence is, ſuch Rulers are a viſible Judgment, and a Curſe upon the People: They are given in wrath and not in mercy. On the contrary, religious Rulers are a publick Bleſſing, as pillars on which the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a People ſtands firm and unſhaken. <hi>The Earth and all the Inhabitants thereof are diſſolved; I bear up the Pillars thereof,</hi> (ſaith the royal Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.3. Were it not for Government, all things would ſoon come to ruin and diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Not only the throne, but the happineſs of
<pb facs="tcp:153890:11"/>Mankind is eſtabliſhed by Righteouſneſs. <hi>Bleſſed art thou, O Lord, When thy King is the Son of Nobles, and thy Princes eat in due Seaſon,</hi> Eccles. 10.17. That is, when the Rulers are Religious, then theſe Mountains bring peace, quietneſs, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and many bleſſings unto the People. Piety and Righteouſneſs are always attended with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other bleſſings. Happy is that Land where Miniſters are burning and ſhining Lights, and the Magiſtrates Peace and Righteouſneſs! It were an eaſie matter to proſecute this Argument. God commandeth Rulers to ſtrengthen the hands of the Righteous, and be a terror to all work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Iniquity. He encourageth them in their duty, and engageth himſelf for their ſafety and reward: He placeth them in the moſt honourable poſt to carry on the work of Reformation, and advance his Kingdom: He intruſteth them with the execution of his Laws, and the cure of Souls: He ſuperviſeth how they uſe their Authority for him: He commends their zeal, and frequently and viſibly puniſheth their negligence, and ſo forth. All theſe heads might be largely ſpoken to, but I ſhall ſtop: From what hath been ſaid, I humbly ſuppoſe, it is the plain and undeniable duty of all Rulers, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover a Zeal for God, and the Reformation of Sinners. But leſt the time ſhould fail, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſhew.</p>
            <p n="3">III. What means are to be uſed in order to the conſciencious Performance of this Duty of diſcovering a Zeal for God, and a Holy Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt Sinners as ſuch, <hi>Thou canſt not bear,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:153890:12"/>&amp;c. I acknowledge, that notwithſtanding all means that can be uſed by men, and even by reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Magiſtrates and Miniſters, it will be found difficult to carry on a Reformation; eſpecially when ſinful Habits are rooted, and Sinners hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a great meaſure through a cuſtom of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, a general Example, worldly Advantages, the Encouragement of the times, or the Prejudice of a prophane Education. In ſuch Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Reformers muſt expect to meet with great Oppoſition, and many Diſcouragements. As they <hi>cannot bear them which are evil,</hi> ſo Sinners can as little bear a Reſtraint, and coming under the Power of Religion: They love their Luſts better than their Souls, and nothing enrages them more than, to be forced to cut off their right Hands, and pluck out their right Eyes. And (alas!) ſuch is the Corruption of depraved Nature, that not a few, whoſe Examples have a great Influence, ſet up as Champions for, and Patrons of Sin and Prophaneneſs. All this muſt be own'd, and is matter of Lamentation. But yet notwithſtanding, ſuch as fear God, muſt not be diſcouraged, or neglect their Duty, <hi>Via Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis ardua eſt, ſed jucunda.</hi> The way of vertue is ſtrait and uneaſy, but yet the pleaſure of the Duty ſurmounts all Difficulties. And if it is the Duty of all in their places, and eſpecially of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, to diſcover a zeal for God, and a Holy Indignation againſt Sinners as ſuch, (as you have heard it is) Then is it their Duty alſo to uſe all lawful means, appointed for the Reformation of Sinners.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:153890:12"/>
            <p>And the firſt that I would recommend to all in general, is a perſonal Reformation. By the Bleſſing of God, this will prove a powerful and convincing Argument. I am ſure, it is moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, that they ſhould prove Inſtrumental to reform others, that take a ſinful Latitude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Such do but harden Sinners in their wickedneſs, even, when they plead moſt zealous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a Reformation. They that would reform others muſt lead the Way. They muſt begin firſt at home, and diſcover their Sincerity, Zeal and Authority, in the Reformation of themſelves and their Families, or ſuch as have any Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon them: Then may they appear boldly for God abroad, and none to make them aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; otherwiſe they muſt expect to hear, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice cura teipſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More eſpecially the religious, Example of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Rulers, Magiſtrates and Miniſters, will be found to have great Influence, <hi>Regis ad exemplar totus componitur Orbis.</hi> The ſame holds true of ſuborninate Rulers in their places. The Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all Ages affords us ſufficient Proof hereof. We read not of any Holy Magiſtrate or Miniſter, but hath done ſomething, nay, much good in his place; or of any bad ones, but have done much hurt. Examples are of greater Force than Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts. They have a ſtrong Influence and a ſecret power over the Conſciences and Minds of Men. Where they are good, they make Sinners their own Accuſers and Judges. He that is impartial, watchful and ſevere over himſelf, hath great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority when he reproveth ſin in others. And if
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153890:13"/>they are not hardned, he is moſt likely to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with them.</p>
            <p>But to think, that God will honour any one to reform others, that hateth to be reformed himſelf, is next to the expecting a Miracle in the moſt unlikely way. What recommended the Chriſtian Religion in all ages, was next unto the Grace of God, that the Propagators thereof led the moſt innocent and holy Lives themſelves, <hi>Non magna loquimur, ſed vivimus.</hi> Our good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples will call loudly to Sinners, if we ſay lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing. And it is a moſt certain Diſcovery of a zeal for God, and a holy Indignation againſt ſin, when we dare not allow it in our ſelves.</p>
            <p>A 2d. mean is, To manifeſt our Hatred of Sin, and our religious Diſpleaſure with Sinners, on all occaſions. They have but little zeal for God, or love to Him, that ſmile upon ſin, or cheriſh Sinners in their Wickedneſs. It is fit the world ſhould know, (as well as God and our own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences) that we look upon ſin, as a ſore &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Evil, an Affront to God, and a Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt his Law; and on Sinners, as enemies to the righteous Government of the World. And if ſo, how can we but frown upon the one, and teſtifie and declare againſt the other? <hi>A froward Heart ſhall depart from me, I will not know a wicked Perſon,</hi> Pſal. 101.4.</p>
            <p>If Sin &amp; Sinners have not our Hearts, it ſavours of Hypocriſy to favour them with our Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. And it excuſeth not here, (how common and plauſible ſoever the Objection, or rather Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>) That Sinners are above us in quality,
<pb facs="tcp:153890:13"/>or ſuch as may not regard our Diſlike of their Ways; nay, that will ſin the more, to add to our Diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>I ſay, this excuſeth not the neglect of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for we are bound to teſtify, (at leaſt ſo far for God) that Sinners of what Rank ſoever may know, that we dare not ſin at their rate. And this may be done ſeveral ways, either by ſilence, by a gentle reproof, by diſcovering ſome diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, by bearing our teſtimony, by removing from, or avoiding the Society of Sinners, and ſo forth: And all this without venturing on the Croſs, further than we are commanded to do, &amp; what I humbly ſuppoſe is the duty of all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that would appear to have any zeal for God, or his Kingdom. But if the Laws of a Land allow it, I think we ought to go yet further; even ſo far as to arraign Sin, and bring incorrigible Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to ſhame or due Puniſhment by our teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, if no other private Methods are like to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim them. Our Faithfulneſs to God and his Intereſt, calls for no leſs at our Hands, what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies ſoever ſeem to attend the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of our Duty. It argues too much, either of a mean or carnal ſpirit, to conſult here with Fleſh and Blood, or to be ſwayed by Intereſt, Cuſtom, or Example. We are to do our duty, and truſt our God. Whatſoever deſerveth our Hatred and Diſpleaſure, therefore ought not to have our Connivance, far leſs our Countenance and Encouragement.</p>
            <p>A 3d. mean is, Earneſt Prayer to God, and Humiliation for the ſins of the Place and Land
<pb facs="tcp:153890:14"/>where we live. They diſcover but little zeal for God's Glory and Kingdom, or concern for the danger of impenitent Sinners, that live ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely, and reſtrain prayer in a time of great Provocation. What! a zeal for God, and yet not lament and bewail his Diſhonour? Any zeal for, or regard to an angry, provoked God, and yet not pray unto him! Any Pity to, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for endangered and ſelf-deſtroying Sinners, and yet not lift up a Petition for them! How inconſiſtent are theſe things? Methinks, if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Honour of God, (of all others the moſt powerful Motive) or Pity unto Sinners, incite and awake us to Prayer and Humiliation, in a time of great Provocation, our own Danger ſhould do it; which we may ſee, when we read, that they only eſcape, and are marked, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Day of God's Viſitation, <hi>that ſigh and cry for all the Abominations that be done where they live,</hi> Ezek. 9.4.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible, that all our Zeal and Endeavours cannot put a ſtop to the ſtrong current of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs. But this calls us ſo much the more to Humiliation and Prayer. And this we are called to, and can do. We can bewail that which we cannot amend. We can humble and afflict our ſelves, and wreſtle with God by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when there is no hope to prevail with Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. And what can we do leſs than mourn over the Violation of God's holy Law, and the Folly, Madneſs, and Danger of Sinners, that haſten their own ruine, and the Judgement of the Lard wherein they live? Surely, our Zeal, if we have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153890:14"/>any, will bring us to our Knees; and if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear them which are evil; yet, as they are Men, Charity calls us to lift up our Prayer to God for them. If not for their Reformation, (ſuppoſing they are incorrigible) yet for the averting of God's Wrath and Judgement, under which the righteous alſo may groan and ſuffer with them.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I have offered nothing, but what I think binds all Chriſtians in general, that would manifeſt any zeal for God. But ſince, not only all Chriſtians as ſuch, are bound to diſcover a zeal for God, but Chriſtian Rulers, Civil and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, in a more eſpecial Manner; therefore I think I am called, to touch alſo at the means to be uſed by them as ſuch. And,</p>
            <p n="1">I. As to civil Rulers or Magiſtrates, Their Zeal for God, Order, and the Advancement of Reformation, (the great End of their Authority and Power) ſhould methinks make them Lovers of thoſe that are good, and a terrour to the evil. Such in their ſeveral Places, whether ſupreme or ſubordinate, are God's Miniſters, and in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Common-wealth, intruſted with the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Laws of God and the Land. The Law is equally a Protection, and Rule to them in the way of their Duty, <hi>They are God's Ordinance for good, and to execute Wrath upon him that doth evil, Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. If then they have any zeal for God, any regard to Juſtice, any ſenſe of their own Duty, or any Diſlike of, or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure againſt thoſe which are evil, They muſt look to it, that the Laws be not broken or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153890:15"/>God's Laws are holy &amp; unalterable, &amp; civil Conſtitutions grounded upon them, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and binding, and of great Force, becauſe of their Correſpondency, and Agreement with the former. Now what good Magiſtrate can ſuffer both to be trampled underfoot? The higheſt Powers (with the ſupreme Magiſtrate, where there is any) makes Laws in order to be inviolably obſerved, and not broken at will, or ſet at nought. And ſubordinate Rulers are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for, and generally intruſted with their Execution. If the former be good Men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the Laws they make are ſo in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. And if the latter are ſuch as do their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then the Laws have all their Force. And is not this the great End and Deſign of Magiſtracy?</p>
            <p>Wicked Men fail not to ſhew and manifeſt their zeal. If placed in Authority, they care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully look to it, that ſuch as the Statutes of <hi>Omri</hi> were, be kept, that the Hands of Sinners be ſtrengthned, and ſo forth. Woeful Experience atteſts this. And ſhould not Chriſtian Rulers then, and ſuch as would be accounted good Men, and a Bleſſing to their Country, ſhew their zeal in ſeeing good Laws put in Execution, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging ſuch as fear God? It is their place to weild the Sword of Juſtice, to ſtrengthen the Hands of the righteous, to diſcourage Sin by Authority, and to bring obſtinate Offenders and Tranſgreſſors to Puniſhment.</p>
            <p>If they fail herein, they defeat the End of Government, they enervate the Laws, &amp; ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Hands of Sinners. What ſhall I ſay? It
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153890:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>is by their Faithfulneſs and Zeal, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come publick Bleſſings, that they gain reſpect with God, and good Men, that they credit and ſtrengthen the Laws wherewith they are intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; and in fine, are in any probability to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Reformation of Sinners, or hinder the ſpreading of Impiety and Prophaneneſs.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, their Indifferency or Partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity makes them a publick Nuiſance, Judgement and Curſe. How then doth it concern them, to diſcover a zeal for God, and by their own Example, and the due Exerciſe of their Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to give force unto the Laws, the Execution of which they are intruſted with? Thus they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at once to be good Men, and good Rulers, and may by God's Bleſſing do much to deſtroy the Miſeries, and ſtop the current of Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="2">II. As to Eccleſiaſtical Rulers or Miniſters; ſuch are to diſcover their Zeal, and anſwer the End of their Office, by the right uſe of the Sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God. Their great Work is to uſe this Sword, ſo as to reach the Conſciences of Sinners.</p>
            <p>Of all Men they ſhould be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, haters &amp; diſcouragers of them which are evil: Not that any outward coercive power belongs to them, or that any pretended zeal can warrant them to move out of their own ſpiritual ſphere. No, their Weapons ſhould not be Carnal, but Spiritual; And their Zeal for God and Charity to Souls ſufficiently diſcovers it ſelf in the conſciencious diſcharge of their Miniſterial Office. This the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153890:16"/>Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſumms up in a few words, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Preach the Word, be inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long ſuffering and doctrine.</hi> And this one rule obſerved, with a holy life, and the exerciſe of that diſcipline againſt Offenders that the Scriptures Warrant, will be a ſufficient and practical proof, that they <hi>cannot bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Rulers are, its true, to be meek and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to all, but their meekneſs is ſo to be tempered with zeal, that they appear not in the leaſt to connive at Sin, far leſs encourage it, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the hands of Sinners.</p>
            <p>Then they are faithful Witneſſes, and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions for the Kingdom of God, when they <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear them which are evil:</hi> That is, when they labour to convince and convert Sinners; and by the Key of Diſcipline, deprive the Ungodly and Prophane of Chriſtian Priviledges. So ſhall their Lord and Maſter approve their Zeal, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their Labours and Fidelity. <hi>Thou canſt not bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much of the heads propoſed for the clearing of the Doctrine; A few words more of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Application, and I ſhall conclude. The liberty I have taken to enlarge already, together with the ſhort preſcribed time allowed, confine me to doe the leſs here, and leave the more for you. Some things I muſt hint at, and theſe I ſhall comprize, and ſhut up in an Addreſs to three ſorts of Men; all bound to diſcover a Zeal for God, and the Reformation of Sinners. I mean Civil Magiſtrates, Eccleſiaſtical Rulers, and all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153890:16"/>Chriſtians as ſuch in their reſpective Places and Relations.</p>
            <p n="1">I. I make bold to addreſs to Civil Magiſtrates; not preſuming to dictate, or teach them their duty, but as a Chriſtian, a Miniſter, and one that breathes after, and prays for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Reformation and Righteouſneſs, to put them in remembrance.</p>
            <p>You Chriſtian Rulers then, high and low, of what denomination ſoever, know, That it will be your Glory, and what will add to the luſtre of your Crown, to deſerve the Approbation of the Text, that you <hi>cannot bear them which are evil. I know, how that,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you, let the Glory of God, the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Reformation, the Senſe of your own Duty, the threatning Clouds that hang over our Land, and the great danger, and growing num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of bold Sinners, ſtir up your Zeal, and awake you unto Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>You ſee, That the Age is become ſo degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and alas, under a profeſſion of Religion; and where Chriſtianity is eſtabliſhed by Law, that the very name of Reformation, as well as the thing, is become ſuſpected and hateful! We ſeem to be aſhamed and afraid of that which our Fathers gloried in. Atheiſm and Prophaneneſs break in upon us like a Flood: And it is to be feared, that all (a heavy Curſe, and Gods righteous Judgment upon us) flows in a great meaſure hence, That ſo few call for, or execute Juſtice, &amp; plead for Truth: Or that <hi>Judgment is turned into Gall,</hi> (to ſpeak in the Language of
<pb facs="tcp:153890:17"/>the Prophet, <hi>Am.</hi> 6.12. <hi>and the Fruit of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs into Hemlock.</hi> Impiety and Prophaneneſs have been ſo long countenanced in this Land, that Sinners are not only multiplied, but become im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and reſolute againſt a Reformation. So that in the way of ſecond Cauſes, nothing is like to reſtrain the general Corruption, but either a ſweeping Scourge with the Sword of Vengeance, or the zealous Execution, and right Uſe of the Sword of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>What can prevent the terrrors of the Lords Wrath, but that ſuch as are called Gods, and bear the Sword, execute Wrath upon him that doth evil, if there is no other way to reform him? How ſingular are our helps and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to advance a Reformation? We have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Laws, grounded upon the law of God, ſufficiently plain and full againſt Prophaneneſs.</p>
            <p>And now the higheſt Powers call for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Laws. To this purpoſe we have had (by Divine Providence) of late years, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many Laws and Proclamations for the ſuppreſſing of Prophaneneſs.</p>
            <p>What remaineth then, but that all you who are intruſted with the execution of the Laws, approve your ſelves to be Miniſters of God; and that every Sin that falls within your Cognizance, run upon the point of the Sword? Methinks, your zeal for God ſhould make you ſpend your moſt angry looks on the boldeſt, and moſt daring Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and bring ſuch as fear not God, to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before you his Vicegerents. Ah, ſhall the Sword of Juſtice ruſt in your hands, while Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="tcp:153890:17"/>are hardned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nity? Shall the beſt Laws prove a dead, or rather a killing Letter, for want of being put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Shall Nurſeries of Prophaneneſs grow up before the eyes of Chriſtian Magiſtrates, &amp; theſe alſo called the Reformed? God forbid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that ruleth over Men, muſt be Juſt, ruling in the fear of God,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.3. Awake then you Miniſters of a jealous God, and make the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of our <hi>Iſrael</hi> aſhamed, nay tremble before you. You have an opportunity put in your hands to doe God Service, ſingular Means and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements. You have the Law on your ſide: You have your Inferiour Officers, and the Command of all the People to attend your Motions.</p>
            <p>Awake then, let not our Sabbaths be prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any longer: Let not the Name of God be blaſphemed: Let not the Holy Laws of the Lord, and the good Conſtitutions of our Land, be dare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly broken and trampled under Foot: Let not our Taverns and Ale-houſes be more frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and full than our Churches. Let not roaring Debauchees, Atheiſts, corrupters of Youth, and prophane Varlets, boaſt of Impunity: Let not the Enemies of God and Godlineſs find Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Encouragement under Chriſtian Rulers. In a word, let not all that is Sacred, be turned into Ridicule, to the Scandal and Wounding of Religion, the diſgrace of Government, the grief of all ſincere and zealous Chriſtians, the joy of Devils and Sinners, the increaſe of Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the haſtning of ſore Judgments upon our Land. <hi>Diſcite Juſtitiam moniti. Be Wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:153890:18"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, O ye Kings, be inſtructed, ye Judges of the Earth. Serve the Lord with Fear, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce with Trembling,</hi> Pſal. 2.10, 11. What ſhall I ſay? Let there be an accompliſhment of the happy Prophecy in our Days; <hi>I will make thy Officers Peace, and thy Exactors Righteouſneſs, Iſa.</hi> 60.17.</p>
            <p n="2">II, A few words to Eccleſiaſtical Rulers: I mean all Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Paſtors of Chriſtian Churches, let me as a remembrancer recommend to ſuch, That they be ambitious of the Character of the Angel of the C. of <hi>Epheſus, Thou canſt not bear them which are evil.</hi> Surely, this is beſt done by Preaching and Living ſin down. None but Angels of Darkneſs do cheriſh Prophaneneſs, or encourage the Prophane. Conſider, Revd. &amp; dear Brethren, it is not a blind Zeal, or for Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, that will credit the Miniſtry, or glorifie God. Piety, Meekneſs, Moderation and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not Strife, Contentions, Wars and Fightings, become the Meſſengers of the Prince of Peace, the meek and loving Jeſus, who ſmartly repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the precipitant Zeal of his Diſciples, that in their Anger would command fire from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; ſaying, <hi>ye know not what ſpirit ye are of,</hi> Luke 9.54, 55. <hi>Woe to them that ſpend themſelves for Circumſtantials and uſeleſs Ceremonies, and would fire Church and State for the Tythe of Mint, Aniſe and Cummin, and yet in the mean time paſs over the weightier matters of the Law, Judgement, Mercy, Faith, and the love of God,</hi> Mat. 23.23. &amp; Luke 11.42. While Men contend for the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, the ſubſtance is loſt.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153890:18"/>
            <p>Some (alas) ſee no need of Reformation; all their Cry is Schiſm, Schiſm. And all becauſe there is not a conſtant Communion externally, even in the moſt unneceſſary and needleſs, irkſome, and troubleſome, if not ſinful things. They that harp ſo much upon this ſtring, conſider not how ſecretly they wound, and reflect upon our Rulers, that would eſtabliſh, or allow, which you pleaſe, a Schiſm by Law, the Spiritual Fathers, the right Reverend Biſhops alſo concurring, and not ſo much as bearing their Teſtimony to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. But ſuch reſtleſs Spirits would do well to goe yet to School, and learn the right and true Notion of Schiſm. If they will not learn from the Scriptures, to which they have been ſo rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally, and frequently referred, yet methinks they being of the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould regard the Judgement of ſome of the greateſt Men, and Lights of that Body in this Point. The Men I ſhall name, (and the moſt learned and valuable Doctors are of their mind) are ſuch as they cannot reaſonably except againſt; and by the evidence of two Witneſſes (inſtead of many that might be produced) they may ſee an end put to the Strife.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the Learned and Reverend <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling worth,</hi> In his Preface to the Author of Charity maintained, his Words are theſe, <q rend="inline">Neither is it always of neceſſity Schiſmatical, to ſeparate from the External Communion of a Church, tho' wanting nothing neceſſary: For if this Church, ſuppoſing to want nothing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, require me to profeſs againſt my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153890:19"/>that I believe ſome Error, tho' never ſo ſmall and Innocent, which I do not Believe, and will not allow me her Communion but upon this condition; in this caſe, the Church for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring this condition is Schiſmatical, and not I, for ſeparating from the Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this let me add the Concluſion of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, <q rend="inline">Let all Men (ſaith he) believe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that only; and endeavour to believe it in the true ſenſe, and require no more of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: And they ſhall ſind this not only a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but the only means to ſuppreſs Hereſie, and reſtore Unity. For he that believes the Scripture ſincerely, and endeavours to believe it in the true ſenſe, cannot poſſibly be a Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. And if no more than this were required of any Man to make him capable of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Communion, then all Men ſo quallified, tho' they were different in opinion,</q> (and I add, <hi>conſequently worſhiped in different places and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi>) <q rend="inline">yet notwithſtanding any ſuch difference, muſt be of neceſſity one in Communion.</q> So far this Learned Man, who had a true Notion of Schiſm.</p>
            <p>The other is the very learned Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> his cool and unbyaſſed thoughts you have. <hi>Iren.</hi> chap. 6. pag. 117. <q rend="inline">Where any Church (ſaith he) retaining Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Doctrine, requires the owning of, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to any unlawful or ſuſpected practice; (mark that) Men may lawfully deny Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to, and Communion with that Church in ſuch things, without incurring the guilt of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153890:19"/>Schiſm;</q> read pag. 119. to the ſame purpoſe. And that this was the Drs. ſettled Judgement not in his younger years only, appears from many other places of his learned Writings. Diſcourſe of <hi>Idol. of Rome,</hi> pag. 7. <q rend="inline">We are ſure (ſaith he) that wilful Ignorance, or chooſing a worſe Church before a better, is a damnable ſin, &amp; unrepented of, deſtroys Salvation.</q> Again, pag. 39. <q rend="inline">That Church is to be judged pureſt, that hath the beſt grounds; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is of neceſſity to Salvation, to embrace the Communion thereof.</q> And in his rational Account of the <hi>Prot. Relig.</hi> p. 291. <q rend="inline">Leſſer Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties cannot in Juſtice make the neceſſary Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Communion narrower than thoſe which belong to the Catholick Church, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> Thoſe things which declare Men Chriſtians, ought to capacitate them for Communion with Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</q> Again, <hi>ibid.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">The main End of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Society, being the Promotion of God's Honour, and Salvation of Mens Souls, the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary Obligation of Men entring into it, is the Advancement of theſe ends to join in all Acts of it, ſo far as they tend to theſe Ends: But if any thing come to be required directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to theſe Ends, thoſe Men, of whom ſuch things are required, are bound not to communicate in thoſe leſſer Societies, where ſuch things are impoſed, but to preſerve their Communion with the Catholick Society of Chriſtians.</q> Again, pag. 331. <q rend="inline">He that ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates only from particular Churches, as to ſuch things as concern not their Being, is only
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153890:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeparated from the Communion of thoſe Churches, and not the Catholick. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuppoſing that all particular Churches, have ſome Errours and Corruptions in them, tho' I ſhould ſeparate from them all, (that is no doubt from thoſe Errours and Corruptions in them) I do not ſeparate from the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the whole Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And the reaſon he ſubjoyns, <q rend="inline">I declare the grounds of my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to be ſuch Errours and Corruptions, which are crept into the Communion of the Churches, and impoſed on me in order to it. I withal declare my readineſs to joyn again, if thoſe Errours and Corruptions be left out.</q> So much, and I think enough from our learned Dr. and Biſhop.</p>
            <p>O that Miniſters would diſcover their zeal for God, in contending not for the ſhadow, but the ſubſtance, not for ſilver Shrines and deluſory Trifles, <hi>but for the Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> as Jude <hi>ver.</hi> 3. Then they would no longer ſow Pillars under Mens Armholes, nor make the Hearts of the righteous ſad, nor ſtrengthen the Hands of Sinners, but ſpend and be ſpent to carry on a happy reformation to the glory of God; that is, they would no longer <hi>bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Once more, a Word to all Chriſtians as ſuch in their reſpective places and relations. Be exhorted Chriſtians to put to your helping hand, as you have any Zeal for God, or Love to religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to advance the reformation of a ſinful and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Age. Let Parents teach and inſpect
<pb facs="tcp:153890:20"/>their Children, and Maſters of Families their Servants; <hi>And let all conſider one another to provoke to love and good Works,</hi> Heb. 10.24. There is a great Emphaſis in the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of that Text, or word tranſlated, <hi>Provoking.</hi> It ſignifies a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking with fervour and zeal, ſmartneſs and ſharpneſs. Now Chriſtians, be thus zealous for God, and valiant for the Truth; throw water on the Fire wherever it breaks out round about you.</p>
            <p>You muſt not mind your own things only, but thoſe alſo of others, and more eſpecially, what the Honour and Glory of God are moſt concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in.</p>
            <p>You muſt not only Pray, Praiſe, Love and Fear God your Selves, but you ought to pity Sinners, that haſten not only their own Ruin, but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Calamity.</p>
            <p>And in order hereunto, if you cannot by your zealous Endeavours, pluck theſe Brands out of the Fire, or prevail with them to conſider the evil and fatal conſequences of their ways; you are called in the next place highly to Value, and zealouſly to Encourage all reforming Magiſtrates, and facilitate their Work to them, and all Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of Juſtice under them; and to prize a Powerful, Faithful, &amp; Laborious Miniſtry. Theſe means God uſually bleſſeth, to convert and doe good to Souls; if Chriſtians were thankful for them and conſcientious to improve them to the beſt advantage, how much good might be done? What ſhall I ſay? Chriſtians, let every one in his place, be valiant for the Truth, Lovers
<pb facs="tcp:153890:21"/>of ſuch as love and fear God, and Haters of all that hate him in his Laws and Kingdom. <hi>Them that honour God, he will honour, and they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe him, ſhall be lightly eſteemed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30.</p>
            <p>Thrice bleſſed are and ſhall they be, of whom the Searcher of Hearts ſhall approve, in this Life, in Death or Judgment, in the words of the Text, <hi>I know, how you cannot bear them which are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to our High, Holy, and Jealous God, who deſerves our zealous Appearance for him, and will reward the Love and Labours of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, to the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, be all Glory, and the Kingdom for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. C.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153890:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
